Guide to the Baker and Wells families papers, 1897-1990.
Baker and Wells families papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Baker and Wells families papers, 1897-1990.
3601
Elizabeth Baker Wells.
14.5 cubic ft.
Correspondence, photographs, diaries, notes, photographs, scrapbooks, articles, a typescript, and sketchbooks.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes research material on Elizabeth Baker Wells' biography of Albert W. Force and other material relating to Cornell history, as well as papers of the Baker and Wells families.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Elizabeth Baker Wells researched the life and Albert W. Force and wrote Albert Force 1897-1970. She also researched and wrote Contributions to Cornell History: Portraits and Memorabilia, 1984.
Albert William Force was born in Waterloo, New York on February 26, 1897. He served with the Army Medical Corps in World War I, and in 1921 he received a B.S. in agriculture from Cornell University. He spent a year as a graduate student and assistant in Cornell's Department of Plant Pathology. He was known in Tompkins County, New York for his interest in local history and antique collecting, and was an authority on Henry Walton, the 19th century American painter. He lived in Forest Home, Ithaca, New York.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Research material on Albert W. Force includes his notes and drawings on mycology from a Cornell University course; photographs; biographical material; news articles; scrapbooks; and a photocopy of Force's will. Also, a carbon typescript draft and a published copy of Albert Force 1897-1970; letters from Elizabeth B. Wells inquiring about Force; and congratulatory letters to Wells on her book. Also copy of Contributions to Cornell History, 1984, a revised edition of her 1978 "Catalogue of Art Works at Cornell University," and "Addendum to Contributions to Cornell History," compiled and edited by Diane B. Nelson, 1990, with background documentation. Also papers of Professor Baker and his son-in-law John Wells, who taught geology at Cornell. Also papers of Elizabeth Baker Wells, who maintained a directory of campus art work.
Also, Correspondence, photographs, diaries, sketchbooks, and other material of William Charles Baker, the Baker family, Elizabeth Baker Wells, and the Wells family.
Additional W.C. Baker items including watercolor: Duplex views: Cayuga Lake above, Mountain with flat valley below; "catalog/price sheet" with miniature samples of views, colored with pencil and typical prices; conte crayon self portrait; pen and ink sketch of large oak tree; envelope with twenty one handmade oil color charts, 1955-1956 (possibly made to test colorfastness), and three published color chart brochures; one sketch book, January 1921, maily pencil rough sketches with notes, some pen, some green pencil, two watercolor; one pen sketch "Elizabeth's First Shoe."
SUBJECTS
Names:
Wells, Elizabeth Baker.; Baker family.; Baker, William Charles.; Force, Albert W.; Nelson, Diane B.; Wells family.; Wells, Elizabeth Baker.; Wells, John.; Cornell University--Art collections.; Cornell University--History.
Subjects:
Antiques.; Local history.; Mycology.; Family--New York (State)
Places:
Forest Home (N.Y.)--History.; Ithaca (N.Y.)--History.; Tompkins County (N.Y.)--History, Local.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photoprints.; Scrapbooks.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Albert W. Force
  - Research material on Force includes Elizabeth B. Wells letters, Contribution to Cornell History, 1984, "Catalogue of Art Works at Cornell University" ( 1978 revision); also, "Addendum to Contributions to Cornell History," compiled and edited by Diane B. Nelson, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook and publications (Box 2)
  - Letters regarding C.U. buildings (Box 3)
- William Charles Baker
  - Letter box, Etaple photos, clipping files, early sketchbooks, Paris photos (Box 4)
  - 21 photos of paintings by Christian Midjo, 20 b/w; one color (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Winter Magic poem (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Framed Midjo piece (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - WC Baker published images (Box 24, Folder 4-6)
  - Notes and clippings (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbooks, 8 sketchbooks (Box 5)
  - ca. 60 files of William Charles Baker writings, notes, essays, and other Baker family photos and documents (Box 7)
- Baker Family
  - 2 studio photo portfolios: William Charles Baker and Anna (190-?), framed envelope of family photos (1890's?) (Box 6)
  - Daguerreotype/tintype (?) folding pair of photos in small jointed frame (Box 6)
  - Anna Baker's Daily Reminder 1901 (red cloth) (Box 6)
  - Blue box of Anna Baker's travel documents (Box 6)
  - Red box of Baker family and friends photos (Box 6)
  - Ring notebook of Baker documents (especially Anna in Berlin as music student) (Box 6)
  - Box of color slides of William Charles Baker art (Box 6)
  - Family portraits, MU-2505; In engraved case (Box 24)
- Elizabeth Baker Wells
  - Calendars (annotated): [195-]-[198-] (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook (1929?-1934/5) (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook ( 1945 ) (Box 8)
  - 1954 world trip diary (Box 8)
  - 1960 Europe diary (Box 8)
  - Passports (Box 8)
  - Bookplate block by William Charles Baker (Box 8)
  - Drafts and notes for catalogue (Box 8)
  - Photos (Box 8)
  - Address book ( 1935-37 ?) (Box 8)
  - Alphabetical file arrangement: small glassed oval photo (of her?) in front, including letters to brother, Robert W. Baker (Box 9)
  - Catalogue notes and correspondence (Box 9)
- John and Elizabeth Wells
  - Marriage ceremony booklet (Box 10)
  - Passports (Box 10)
  - Letters and documents: John West Wells, Elizabeth Baker Wells, Maida and Raymond Wells, 1929-1957/6 (Box 10)
- John West Wells and Elizabeth Baker Wells
  - Letter, photos, John West Wells, Maida and Raymond Wells, Pemberton West (Box 11)
  - John West Wells scrapbook (Box 11)
  - Nitwitziana (Elizabeth Baker Wells, 1929 ) (Box 11)
  - Elizabeth Baker Wells' masters' thesis (Box 11)
  - Wells family Bible, inscription 1864 (his grandfather) (Box 11)
- Wells Family
  - Box of West and Stull photos, some identified by Maida West Wells (Box 12)
  - John West Wells calendar diaries, 1918-1924, 1927, 1932 (9 vols.) (Box 12)
  - Manticoceras log book ( 1956-1970 ) (Box 12)
  - Maida West's scrapbook (including John West Wells school records, 1920s-1930s) (Box 12)
  - Eleven photo albums, 1914-1935 (Box 12)
  - Framed silhouette of John Crouch Wells (Box 13)
  - Framed marriage certificate of George H. West and Matilda A. Burton, Mar. 30, 1899 (Box 13)
  - John West Wells' bookplate block (William Charles Baker design) (Box 13)
  - Manilla envelope relating to John West Wells's geology classes (Box 13)
  - Ten photo albums (John West Wells), 1920-1945 (Box 13)
  - Raymond Wells' 1907 notebook relating to his process (Box 13)
  - Bible (Philadelphia: M. Carey, 1816 ), includes family records, on pp. 677-680 ( 1806-1867 ) plus 3 leaves of added mss. to 1934 (Box 14)
  - Green cardboard box of family photos (turn of century) (Box 14)
  - Maida West Wells: diaries, 16 vols., 1916-1937, pocket notebook, "Incidental Expenses," Shakespeare Birthday Book, 1900, (Christmas lists, 1920-1935 ) (Box 14)
  - Raymond Wells: eleven technical notebooks, one dated 1909 (Box 14)
  - Passport photos, 1954-1982 (manilla routing envelope) (Box 14)
  - 2 white envelopes of glass photos (Box 14)
  - Long photo roll of 1914 class, Homer Academy (Box 14)
  - 6 folders of family photos (Box 14)
  - 5 large family photos (including studio portraits of Maida and Raymond Wells) (Box 14)
  - Framed pencil sketch: "Maida West Wells" signed Carl J. Becker, according to John West Wells, "a disappointed suitor" (Box 14)
  - William Charles Baker scrapbook, with Elizabeth Baker Wells' notes, mostly pen and ink sketches (Box 16)
  - William Charles Baker portfolios (15), cover titles or Elizabeth Baker Wells tags:
    - 1. Ahrens/Bertling [graphic works by Carl Ahrens (Canada) and Walter Bertling (Buffalo)] (Box 17)
    - 2. Large photos (old label: Lake Paintings) (Mapcase-folder 1)
    - 3. 2 etchings (matted): Going Home, Imaginary Woodland (Box 18)
    - 4. 4 self portraits (2 present, one still at Sheldrake and one at Alexandria) (Box 18)
    - 5. Pastels and Life Class (Box 18)
    - 6. Art (4 oils) (Box 15)
    - 7. Clippings (Box 15)
    - 8. Pen and ink sketches of birds (etc.) (Box 15)
    - 9. Plants and trees ... PHOTOGRAPHS (Box 15)
    - 10. 1 drawing of gravel pit (William Charles Baker bookplate) etchings (Box 16)
    - 11. Series matted and typed descriptions (Box 15)
    - 12. Clippings and notes (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - 13. Sketches and photos (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - 14. "Reproductions of pix he liked." (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - 15. Watercolor sketchbook (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Brown paper portfolio with black straps:
    - a. 2 pen and ink drawings by Raymond Wells (Mapcase-folder 1)
    - b. Certificates: (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 1. Raymond Wells, Wagner Free Institute of Science, Philadelphia, Chemistry, 1899 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 2. Elizabeth Baker (Wells), University of State of New York (Ithaca High School) diploma, 1924 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 3. _______, Ithaca School diploma, 1924 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 4. John West Wells, University of State of New York (Homer Academy and Union School) college entrance diploma, 1924 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 5. ______, Homer School diploma, 1924 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 6. Maida West (Wells), Daughters of the American Revolution, admission, 1915 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 7. ______, Taconic School diploma, 1905 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 8. John Edwin Wells, Friends Central School, Philadelphia, diploma, 1900, 9. Raymond Wells, Friends Central School, Philadelphia, diploma, 1893 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 10. ______, University of Pennsylvania, B.Sc. (Chem.), diploma, 1904 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 11. John West Wells, University of Pittsburgh, B.Sc., diploma, 1928 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 12. ______, Cornell University, M.A., diploma, 1930 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 13. ______, Society of the Sigma Xi, membership, 1930 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 14. ______, National Research Council, research fellow, 1933 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 15. ______, Cornell University, Ph.D. diploma, 1933 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 16. ______, National Academy of Science, member, 1968 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 17. Elizabeth Baker (Wells), Cornell, M.A., 1930 (Mapcase-folder 1)
      - 18. ______, Society of the Sigma Xi, membership, 1930 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Hockey stick 1924, Elizabeth Baker Wells, Mu. 975